<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Orders and articles granted by the high and mightie Lords of the States General of the Vnited Prouinces, concerning the erecting of a VVest India Companie together with the priuiledges and rights giuen vnto the same.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845691</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845691</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10609</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10609)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1282:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Orders and articles granted by the high and mightie Lords of the States General of the Vnited Prouinces, concerning the erecting of a VVest India Companie together with the priuiledges and rights giuen vnto the same.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
                  <author>West-Indische Compagnie (Netherlands)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. M.DC.XXI. [1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerning the formation of the Nederlandsche West-Indische Compagnie.</note>
                  <note>Publication place from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>West-Indische Compagnie (Netherlands)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ORDERS <hi>AND</hi> ARTICLES GRANTED BY THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE LORDS THE STATES GENERAL OF THE VNITED PROVINCES,</p>
            <p>Concerning the erecting of a <hi>VVeſt Indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Companie:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with the Priuiledges and rights giuen vnto the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRINTED ANNO DOM. M.DC.XXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:2"/>
            <p>THe States Generall of the vnited Prouinces, vnto all thoſe that ſhall ſee theſe, greeting. We make knowne, that we conſidering the good of theſe Lands, and the welfare of the inhabitants of them, to conſiſt principally in the nauigation and traffike which in all times out of theſe Countries with good ſucceſſe and bleſſings in all kingdomes and countries haue continued. And deſiring that the ſaid inhabitants not onely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and keepe their former nauigations and traffikes, but likewiſe as much as is poſſible increaſe the ſame, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally according to the treaties, alliances, contracts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſes concerning the traffike and nauigation with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, Commonwealths and Nations in former times made, which we vnderſtand in all points to be kept and obſerued. And we perceiuing that without a common helpe, aſſiſtance and meanes of a generall Companie, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be vndertaken in the places hereafter ſpecified for to get profit and to maintaine and defend the ſame, in regard of piracies, extorſions and other like matters happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch long nauigations. We haue in regard of theſe and other weightie reaſons and conſiderations mouing vs vnto the ſame as likewiſe ripe deliberations of our Counſels, and other pregnant and weightie occaſions mouing vs in like maner found good, that the nauigation, traffike and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce in the quarters of the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> and other places named hereafter in times following, no more ſhall be exerciſed and vſed then by common and vnited power of Merchants and inhabitants of theſe Countries, and that to the ſame purpoſe ſhall be erected a generall Companie, which we in regard of our ſingular affection and loue to the common good, and to preſerue the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſame in traffike and welfare, ſhall maintaine and ſtrengthen with help, fauour and aſſiſtance, for as much
<pb facs="tcp:10609:3"/> as the preſent ſtate and condition of theſe countries in any maner of wayes can permit, prouiding for the ſame a fit grant, with priuiledges and liberties, here following: viz. That within the terme of foure and twentie yeares, none of the natiues or inhabitants of theſe Countries, otherwiſe then onely by the authoritie of the vnited Companie of theſe vnited Prouinces, or from any other country ſhall nauigate or traffike vpon the coaſts and lands of <hi>Africa,</hi> from <hi>Topica, Cancri,</hi> vntill <hi>Cabo de bonna Eſperanca,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the countries of <hi>America</hi> or <hi>Weſt India,</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the South end of <hi>Terra noua,</hi> through the ſtraight of <hi>Magellanus le Maire</hi> or other ſtraights or paſſages thereabout, vntill the ſtraight of <hi>Anian,</hi> as well vpon the North as South ſea, neither vpon any Ilands either at the one or other ſide, or betwixt them both ſituated; likewiſe neither vpon the <hi>Auſtriall</hi> or Southlands lying betwixt both <hi>Meridians,</hi> touching at the Eaſt ſide <hi>Cabo de bonna Eſperanca,</hi> and at the Weſt ſide, the Eaſt ſide of <hi>Noua Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea,</hi> incluſiue. And if any man without leaue of the ſaid Companie ſhall ſaile or traffike into any of theſe aforeſaid limits granted vnto this Companie, the ſhips and goods ſhall be forfeited, hauing traffiked in any of the aforeſaid parts, which immediatly euery way ſhall be taken and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon by the Companie, and kept for the vſe and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the ſame. And in caſe ſuch ſhips or goods ſhall be ſold, or landed in other countries or ports, ſhall the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant venturers and participants be anſwerable for the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the ſhips and goods, and be conuicted for the ſame, with this caution, that thoſe that before this graunt of theſe or other countries are ſailed vnto any of theſe coaſts, may ſell their goods and returne backe againe in theſe lands; or otherwiſe vntill their grant is expired (if they haue gotten any before this time) continue, and not longer, obſeruing that no body now at the beginning ſhall ſend any ſhips or goods into the parts in this Patent comprehended, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding at the ſame time perhaps the Companie be not fully concluded, prouiding for the ſame as is fit, and
<pb facs="tcp:10609:3"/> againſt them that wilfully againſt our good intention ſhall ſeeke to wrong the generall good. We vnderſtand neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe that it ſhall be free for euery one to fetch ſalt from <hi>Ponte del Re,</hi> but vpon conditions and inſtructions by vs allowed or to be allowed, without otherwiſe in any maner to be tied vnto this grant.</p>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>2</head>
               <p>That moreouer the ſaid Companie in our name and by our authoritie ſhall haue power, within the limits here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet downe, to make contracts and alliances with the Princes and natiues of the countries herein comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as likewiſe to build forts and ſtrong holds, to chuſe gouernours, and men for warres, Officers of iuſtice, and all other neceſſary vſes for the conſeruation of good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, policie and iuſtice, as for the aduancement of trading and traffiking ſhall be required; as likewiſe to depoſe and put downe, and to ſubſtitute other in their places, as they ſhall finde conuenient. Furthermore they ſhall ſearch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and not vninhabited places to plant the ſame, and do euery thing that will be good for the ſeruice and profit of the Countrie, and which the increaſe of traffike will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. And theſe of the Companie ſhall from time to time communicate to vs, and deliuer ſuch contracts and allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as they ſhall make with the ſaid Princes and nations, beſides the ſituations of the forts, places of defence, and plantations by them taken in hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>3</head>
               <p>Obſeruing that the Companie hauing choſen a Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and conceiued inſtructions for him, he ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by vs, and receiue his commiſſion. And the ſaid Gouernour generall ſhall as well as other Vice or Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute gouernors, Commanders and Officers, be ſworne both vnto Vs and the Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>4</head>
               <p>And in caſe the ſaid Companie in any of the places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned happen by fained friendſhip to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or ill vſed, or that any ſummes of mony or merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes
<pb facs="tcp:10609:4"/> truſted abroad without reſtitution or paiment for the ſame be detained, that they ſhall ſee to repaire the damage, according to the cauſe, and as for their abilitie ſhall be moſt requiſite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>5</head>
               <p>And becauſe for the plantation, ſafetie and defence of this traffike, ſome men of warre of neceſſitie muſt be leuied, we will prouide for the ſaid Companie ſuch Commanders, ſouldiers and enginers as ſhall be requiſite, though vpon condition they ſhall be paid by the ſaid Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>6</head>
               <p>Which beſides the oath made vnto vs and his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſhall likewiſe be ſworne to follow the directions and commandements of the Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>7</head>
               <p>That the Prouoſts of the Companie ſhall haue power and authoritie in theſe countries to take and apprehend ſuch ſouldiers and men of warre as ſhall be entred into the ſeruice of this Companie, and bring them to ſhipboard, in whatſoeuer cities, townes or iuriſdictions they ſhall be found: vpon condition the ſaid Prouoſts ſhall aforehand giue notice of it vnto the Officers and Magiſtrates of the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>8</head>
               <p>That we ſhall not take any ſhips, ordinance or munition from this Companie for the vſe of theſe Countries, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the ſaid Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>9</head>
               <p>Moreouer we haue granted and yeelded vnto the ſaid Compan e, and grant and yeeld by theſe preſents, that all their ſhips and goods ſhall paſſe freely, without paying any cuſtome or tole due in theſe vnited Prouinces: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any forreiners may be partakers in the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, which in that regard ſhall enioy like priuiledges with the free inhabitants of theſe countries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>10</head>
               <p>That this Companie for the firſt eight yeares ſhall pay
<pb facs="tcp:10609:4"/> nothing for conuoy for their goods either comming in, or to be ſent into the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> and other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in the ſame limitation comprehended: and is reſerued and concluded, that in caſe at the end of the firſt eight yeares the ſtate and condition of theſe countries cannot admit the ſaid priuiledge of eight yeares to be continued for certaine yeares more, that the goods to be ſent from theſe parts, as likewiſe the wares of theſe aforeſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries being to be tranſported in the conuoyes and licenſes, ſhall not be higher taxt or charged then they are now, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we are in warres againe, in which caſe all the aforeſaid goods and wares ſhall not be taxed higher then they were immediatly before the truce made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>11</head>
               <p>And becauſe this Companie may be well gouerned and to the moſt profit and contentment of all the partakers, we haue ordered that the gouernment of the ſame ſhall conſiſt in fiue Courts of Committees or Commiſſioners, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which ſhall haue the adminiſtration of foure ninth parts; one in <hi>Zealand,</hi> for two ninth parts; one about the <hi>Maes,</hi> for one ninth part; one in North <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for one ninth part; and the fift in <hi>Vrieſland,</hi> the citie and Land likewiſe for a ninth part, vpon conditions ſet downe in the Regiſter of our reſolutions, as appeares by the Act concerning the ſame by vs deliuered. And the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deſtitute of Courts, ſhall be furniſhed with ſo many Commiſſioners, as they ſhall bring a hundred thouſand gilders vnto this Companie, and they ſhall be diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the other Courts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>12</head>
               <p>The Court of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhall conſiſt of twentie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners; the Court of <hi>Zealand</hi> of twelue; the Courts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and North <hi>Holland,</hi> euery one of fourteene; and the Court of <hi>Vrieſland,</hi> citie and land, likewiſe of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene, vnleſſe hereafter it appeare the ſaid not to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, in which caſe we will at our liking and aduice of the nineteene increaſe the number of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:10609:5"/>
               <head>13</head>
               <p>And by theſe is granted authoritie vnto the States of the aforeſaid Prouinces, either before their ordinarie Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or the Magiſtrate of the cities in their Prouinces, to take ſuch an order for the regiſtring and ſubſcribing of the partakers and Commiſſioners, as they ſhall finde agreeable vnto the cuſtomes and lawes of their Prouinces; prouided alwayes that none ſhall be choſen to be a Commiſſioner in the Court at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> vnleſſe he put ſix thouſand gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſtocke of his owne in the ſaid Companie; but in the Court of <hi>Zealand,</hi> as likewiſe in the Courts about the <hi>Maes,</hi> the Court in North Holland and <hi>Vrieſland,</hi> they ſhall not be choſen Commiſſioners, if they bring not vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie foure thouſand gilders a peece.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>14</head>
               <p>That the Commiſſioners ſhall attend the ſpace of ſixe yeares, and at the end of the ſame, one third part ſhall be remoued by bils to be drawne; and two yeares after, a like third part to be remoued; and likewiſe two yeares after, with the laſt third part to be done; and ſo from time to time to diſcharge the elder in office. And in place of the diſmiſt or deceaſed, or for any reaſons put by, ſhall be nominated three perſons by the Commiſſioners, as well that are in place, as that are remoued, as likewiſe by the chiefe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipants and vndertakers, that in perſon and at their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges will come at the Court. And out of theſe three, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Prouinces, their Deputies or Magiſtrates ſhal chuſe new Commiſſioners, and continually ſupply the places va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant: and ſhall be accounted chiefe participants all theſe that as much ſtocke of their owne bring in, as the aforeſaid Commiſſioners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <head>15</head>
               <p>The accounts of the rigging and ſetting foorth of the ſhips and other things concerning the ſame, ſhall be made within the ſpace of three moneths after the departure of the ſame; and within a moneth after ſhall be ſent copies of the ſame vnto vs and the ſeuerall Courts. And concerning
<pb facs="tcp:10609:5"/> the returnes, and the ſale of the ſame, the Courts (whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we ſhall finde it conuenient, or any of the Courts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it) ſhall be bound to giue vs and one another notice of all their ſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>16</head>
               <p>Euery ſix yeares ſhall the reckonings be giuen vp of all voyages and returnes, profits and dammages of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie: viz. one of the traffike, and another of the warres, ſeperatly; which reckonings ſhall be done publikly, and after bils affixed, that euery one being intereſſed, may come at the making vp of theſe accounts. And in caſe before the end of the ſeuenth yeare the ſame be not done, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall loſe their prouiſions, and ſhall be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the vſe of the poore, and they neuertheleſſe be bound to make their reckonings as before, within ſuch a time, and vpon ſuch penalties as ſhall be decreed by vs againſt ſuch delinquents and infringers. And this notwithſtanding there ſhall be made diſtributions as many times as ſhall be proued and certified ten in the hundred to be gotten by traffike.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>17</head>
               <p>No man ſhall during the time of this grant, haue power to draw his cappitall or ſtocke from the Companie; and likewiſe no new partakers in the meane time ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: but in caſe at the expiring of the foure and twentie yeares, it ſhall be thought conuenient to continue the ſaid Companie, or to erect a new one, ſhall be made a finall rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning and eſtimation or priſe by the nineteene, with our knowledge of euery thing concerning this Companie, as likewiſe of the neceſſary charges the Companie hath bin at: and then euery one may chuſe whether he will draw his mony out or in the enſuing Companie keepe wholy or in part. And in ſuch caſe the Companie ſhall be bound to take the remaining things at her charge, and content the reſt of the partakers that ſhall be willing to ſeperate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Companie, euery one according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion; and that at ſuch dayes of paiment as the nineteene
<pb facs="tcp:10609:6"/> with our aduice ſhall find conuenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>18</head>
               <p>That whenſoeuer a generall meeting of the aforeſaid Courts ſhall be appointed, there ſhall meete nineteene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, eight from the Court of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> foure from <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> two from the <hi>Maes,</hi> two from the Northern parts of <hi>Holland,</hi> two from <hi>Vrieſland,</hi> and alſo the citie and land, prouided that the ninetene perſons or as many more as we ſhall thinke fit by vs ſhall be appointed and choſen, for to giue their beſt directions for the diſpatching of the affairs of this Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>19</head>
               <p>By which generall aſſembly of the ſaid Courts, all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning this Companie ſhall be propounded and concluded, with caution that in regard of matters of warre our reſolution ſhall be required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>20</head>
               <p>At the ſaid generall meetings ſhall be reſolued when any ſhips, and how many, and towards what coaſts ſhal be ſent or the generall good of the Companie, hauing no Court power to do any thing without a generall reſolution of the reſt. And in caſe any of theſe Courts might happen to be careleſſe and negligent in the accompliſhing of theſe reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, we haue giuen and giue by theſe ſame the ſaid ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall meetings, authoritie and power to cauſe offenders and delinquents to make reparation for their faults, and requeſted ſhall lend thereunto our helping hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>21</head>
               <p>The ſaid generall meeting ſhal be kept the firſt ſix yeares at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the next two enſuing yeares in <hi>Zealand,</hi> and ſo from time to time in the two aforeſaid places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>22</head>
               <p>The Commiſſioners by the Companie ſent to the ſaid meetings or elſewhere, ſhall haue for their diet and wages foure gilders euery day, beſides the mony for the boate, ſhip or wagons: prouided that theſe that ſhall trauell from the one to the other citie, to frequent and viſit the Courts
<pb facs="tcp:10609:6"/> as Commiſſioners and Aſſiſtants, ſhall receiue neither the one nor the other from the Companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <head>23</head>
               <p>And if happened in the ſaid generall meetings any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great weight &amp; moment to occurre, which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Courts could not agree, and did finde difficultie if they ſhould ouerrule one another, we haue taken vpon vs the deciding of the ſame, and what we ſhall finde good ſhall be followed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>24</head>
               <p>Within the ſpace of a moneth hence ſhall be giuen no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice by bils affixed, to all inhabitants both of theſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countries, that at the expiration of the fiue next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing moneths, beginning from the firſt of Iune, may be admitted &amp; receiued, and pay their capitall ſums in three paiments, viz. a third part at the end of the fiue moneths aforeſaid, and the other two third parts within the three next enſuing yeares, vnleſſe afterwards it be found more conuenient to take longer time, of which the partakers ſhall be aduertiſed by bils affixed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <head>25</head>
               <p>The Ships returning from their iourneys are to land at the ſame places they departed: and if it do happen that any ſhips by reaſon of winde &amp; wether land in other parts, as thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> or the North parts in <hi>Zealand,</hi> or in the <hi>Maes,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>Zealand</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>Vrieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with their aſſociates in any other parts, that neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe euery Court ſhall haue the ouerſight &amp; adminiſtration of his ſhips and goods, and ſhall haue power to ſend the ſhips and goods to the places where their owne Courts are kept, or hire other ſhips or veſſels to conuey the goods to the places aforeſaid, with this clauſe and caution, that the Commiſſioners ſhall preſent themſelues at the places where the ſhips &amp; goods ſhall be arriued, without vſing any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors or deputies in their name. And in caſe it be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for them to trauell vnto thoſe places, they ſhall leaue the charge &amp; adminiſtration vnto the Commiſſioners
<pb facs="tcp:10609:7"/> of the Court next to the landing of ſhip and goods.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>26</head>
               <p>If any of the Courts aforeſaid receiueth any wares, of which any of the other is vnprouided, the ſaid ſhall be bound to prouide the other according to her abilitie, and the ſame being ſold, ſend more. That likewiſe the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Court before mentioned, ſtanding in need of any perſons for rigging of their ſhips or otherwiſe, ſhall ſhew the ſame vnto any other Court or Courts, without v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any factors or agents to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>27</head>
               <p>In caſe any Prouinces ſhall appoint an Agent for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the monies from the Participants in their precinct, and to put the ſame in their Court, and to procure paiment of the diſtributions, he ſhall be admitted in the ſaid Court, for to be informed and inſtructed of the out dealings, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and incomings, prouided he bring into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie filtie thouſand gilders ſtocke or aboue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <head>28</head>
               <p>The Commiſſioners ſhall haue one in the hundred of all goods going out or comming in, as likewiſe of all priſes or taken goods; but of ſiluer and gold but a halfe in the hundred: of which prouiſion the Court of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhall receiue foure ninth parts, the Court in <hi>Zealand</hi> two ninth parts, the Court about the <hi>Maes</hi> a ninth part, the Court of <hi>Vrieſland</hi> ioyned with the citie and land a ninth part, the Court of North <hi>Holland</hi> likewife a ninth part,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="article">
               <head>29</head>
               <p>Prouided alwayes that they ſhall receiue but once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for the ordenance and ſhips, but none at all of the ſhips, ordenance and other things wherewith we ſhall aſſiſt the ſaid Companie; neither of the monies they ſhall take vp for the vſe of the Companie, neither for the goods they ſhall ſell, neither ſhall they bring in any accounts for the attendance and charges of diet and trauell of thoſe they may appoint or ſend for the ſetting forth of the ſhips, or buying of the goods thereunto required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:10609:7"/>
               <head>30</head>
               <p>The keepers of the accounts and of the caſhes likewiſe, ſhall haue their wages paid out of the prouiſion of the Commiſſioners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="article">
               <head>31</head>
               <p>The Commiſſiones ſhall not ſell or deliuer any ſhips or goods or wares vnto the Companie either wholy or partly belonging vnto them; neither ſhall they buy or procure to be bought for them any merchandizes or goods from the Companie, directly or indirectly for themſelues, nor hold in any part of the bargaine. In caſe they faile therein, they ſhall forfeit their prouiſion of one yeare (which ſhal be giuen vnto the poore) and themſelues diſcharged of their places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="article">
               <head>32</head>
               <p>The Commiſſioners ſhall be bound to giue notice by bils affixed, of the merchandizes and goods they newly haue receiued, becauſe euery one may know it before they are ſold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="article">
               <head>33</head>
               <p>And if any of the Commiſſioners happens to decay in his eſtate, that he be not able to make good and giue ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for matters truſted vnto him in regard of his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, which might cauſe damage, their ſtocke in the Companie ſhall be anſwerable for the ſame, being as a pledge and ſecuritie for their true adminiſtration. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if any of the participants for goods bought or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, be indebted vnto the Companie, and decayes in his eſtate, that he be not able to pay his debts, his ſtocke in the Companie ſhall be anſwerable for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="article">
               <head>34</head>
               <p>The Commiſſioners of the aforeſaid Courts ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for their keepers of caſh and accounts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="article">
               <head>35</head>
               <p>That all the wares of this Companie to be ſold by weight, ſhall be ſold and deliuered by the weight of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam</hi> onely; and leaue ſhall be giuen to weigh the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:10609:8"/> in the ſhips or ſtore houſes, without paying any taxes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt or weigh mony, vpon condition neuertheleſſe that the ſame being ſold, ſhall be deliuered at the weigh-houſe, and pay impoſt and weigh-mony as many times as they ſhall be ſold, as all other goods of like nature are vſed to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="article">
               <head>36</head>
               <p>That the Commiſſioners or their goods ſhall not be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted or troubled for to haue rekoning of the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Companie, neither for the wages due vnto any hauing bin employed by the Companie; but pretending any ſuch matter, they ſhall be bound to call them before the ordinary Iudges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="article">
               <head>37</head>
               <p>Any ſhips coming home, the Generals or Commanders of the fleete, ſhip or ſhips, ſhall be bound to come vnto vs within ten dayes after their arriuall, and make report vnto vs of the ſucceſſe of their voyage, as well by writing as by word of mouth, as we ſhall finde conuenient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="article">
               <head>38</head>
               <p>And if it happens (which is not to be thought) that any ſhould croſſe the nauigation, trafficke or trading of the Companie, againſt the vniuerſall lawes, contracts, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and entercourſes, it ſhall be lawfull for the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to defend her ſelfe, and take their courſe according to the inſtructions giuen by vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="article">
               <head>39</head>
               <p>Furthermore we haue promiſed and promiſe by theſe, that we will maintaine and defend the Companie in her free nauigation and traffike, and aſſiſt the ſame to the ſaid purpoſe, with the ſumme of ten hundred thouſand gilders to be paid within the ſpace of fiue yeares, and the firſt two hundred thouſand gilders ſhall be furniſhed as ſoone as the participants haue brought in their firſt paiment of their ſtocke promiſed: prouided alwayes that for the firſt ten hundred thouſand gilders we ſhall receiue profit and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage as the other participants ſhall do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:10609:8"/>
               <head>40</head>
               <p>And in caſe it do happen the Companie ſhall be ſtrongly aſſaulted and inuaded in any of the aforeſaid parts, we ſhall aſſiſt her (theſe countries in any maner of ways being able to do it) with ſixteene ſhips of warre, the leaſt being three hundred tunne, beſides foure pinnaces, the leaſt ſhall be foure ſcore tunne, being of euery thing neceſſary well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of ordenance both of braſſe and iron, and fit quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of munition, double hangings, ſailes, ropes, ankers, and other neceſſaries, as ſhall be fit for any great voyage; prouided that the ſaid afterwards ſhall be manned, victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and kept at the charge of the Companie, vpon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſaid Company ſhall ſet forth likewiſe ſixteen ſhips and foure pinnaces furniſhed as ours, for to defend the Companie from her enemies, as likewiſe to aſſault them. And our ſaid ſhips of warre ſhall ioyne with the ſhips of the Companie, and ſhall go forth vnder one Admirall, to be choſen by vs with aduice of the foreſaid Courts or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall meetings, and ſhall follow our directions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, agreeable to the reſolutions of the Company, to make warres againſt their enemies. But the ſhips of the Companie being loaden, ſhall not hazard themſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great neceſſitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="article">
               <head>41</head>
               <p>And if it ſhall happen that the charges of the warres in our countries here do grow leſſe, and increaſe in the parts aforeſaid, we haue promiſed and promiſe by theſe preſents to giue as much aide and aſſiſtance vnto the Companie as theſe countries ſhall be able to permit, and the ſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Companie ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="article">
               <head>42</head>
               <p>Moreouer we haue ordered, that if it happen in time of warres any priſes to be taken within the ſaid limits of the Companie, as well from their enemies as pirates, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ading and aſſiſting this Companie, as likewiſe the goods that ſhall be ſeiſed vpon by vertue of our Proclamations, all neceſſary charges, and the dammages of the Companie
<pb facs="tcp:10609:9"/> ſuffered by the taking of priſes, beſides the right of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie in qualitie of Admirall, according to our reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made the firſt of April, <hi>Anno</hi> 1602, and the tenth part belonging to the Officers, mariners and ſouldiers that haue made the priſes, being deducted, they ſhall remaine at the diſpoſition of the Companie, which ſhall be bound to keepe reckonings aſunder of the ſame. And the profit or benefit of the ſaid priſes, ſhall be employed or beſtowed to the ſetting forth of ſhips, and paying of the men of warre, as likewiſe to the making of fortifications, the putting in garriſons, and other like matters of warre and defence both by water and land, without making any diſtributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vnleſſe it did appeare the ſaid profit and benefit to be ſo great, that without weakning the defence of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and all charges of the warres being deducted, a good portion might be deuided, ſeperated from the commerce. And the diſtribution ſhall be made in this manner: a tenth part ſhall be giuen for the generall good of theſe countries, and the reſt ſhall be deuided amongſt the Participants of the Companie <hi>pro rato</hi> and according to their ſtocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="article">
               <head>43</head>
               <p>Prouided alwayes that the goods and priſes by vertue of our Proclamations ſeiſed vpon and brought in, ſhall be cenſured by the Iudges of the Admiraltie where they are landed, and iudged whether they be lawfull priſes or not: And during the ſuite the adminiſtration of the ſaid goods, after a due Inuentorie made, ſhall remaine vnto the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, reſeruing the reſidue for thoſe that by the ſentence of the Admiraltie might finde themſelues aggrieued. And the Vendumaiſter or outcrier, and the other officers of the Admiraltie, ſhall not pretend any thing of the priſes bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited or ſold by the Companie, they hauing had nothing to do with the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="article">
               <head>44</head>
               <p>The Commiſſioners of this Companie ſhall be bound by oath, to be true and faithfull in their adminiſtration, to keepe good reckonings of their dealings, to procure the
<pb facs="tcp:10609:9"/> moſt benefit of the Companie, and to auoide all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and dammage as much as ſhall be in their power; that they ſhall not fauour any of the greateſt Participants more then the leaſt, either in the bringing in of their ſtockes, or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the diſtributions: that of thoſe that ſhall owe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Companie, they ſhall not fauour the one more then the other: that they as long as they ſhall be Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, ſhall keepe ſuch ſtocke in the Companie as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed by this grant; as likewiſe that they ſhall keepe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue euery point and article here aboue mentioned, and procure to be held and kept according to their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="article">
               <head>45</head>
               <p>All which priuiledges, liberties and exemptions, beſides the aſſiſtance afore mentioned in euery point and article here aboue, we haue granted vnto the ſaid Companie after good aduice, and do grant by theſe, promiſe and giue by theſe promiſing to procure that they ſhall enioy the ſame without any diſquietneſſe or hinderance. We order like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the ſaid ſhall be kept by all Magiſtrates. Officers and ſubiects of theſe vnited Prouinces, without doing any thing contrary vnto the ſame, either directly or indirectly, within or without theſe vnited Prouinces, vpon paines to be puniſhed both in body and goods, as enemies of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good and infringers of our orders. Promiſing beſides to maintaine the Companie in all points aforeſaid, by all treaties of peace, alliances, entercourſes, with the neighbour Princes, kingdomes and countries, not ſuffering any thing to be done contrary to the ſame. Wherefore wee charge and command directly all Gouernours. Iuſtices, Officers, Magiſtrates and inhabitants of theſe vnited Prouinces, that they permit and ſuffer the ſaid Company and Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to enioy peaceably and without any diſturbance the effect of this grant, conſent and priuiledge, ceaſing by this all other matters ordered to the contrary. And becauſe none might pretend ignorance of theſe, we haue commanded
<pb facs="tcp:10609:10"/> that the principall points of this Grant ſhall be made knowne either by publication or affixing of bils, where it ſhall be required, iudging the ſame to be for the good of this Countrie.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10609:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
